Guide to the James C. Morehead, Jr. Papers/Visuals, c. 1912-1990 MS 477
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
James C. Morehead, Jr. architectural papers and visual materials
c. 1912-1990
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Morehead, James C., Jr., 1913-1999
MS 477
7 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
This collection contains educational materials including manuscripts and visuals for books on architectural construction methods. Also included are "A Walking Tour of Rice University" glass plate negatives (c. 1912-1950) given to Morehead by William Ward Watkin for use in Morehead's construction class. The collection also contains many photographs and slides of buildings and unique architecture at Rice University.
Biographical Note
James Caddall (Bud) Morehead, Jr. was born in Bradenton, Florida on October 29, 1913. He graduated from Princeton University in 1935 with a degree in Mathematics and then received an Architecture degree from the Carnegie Institute of Technology in 1939. He served in the U.S. Army during World War II and rose to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. He was also elected a Fellow in the American Institute of Architects in 1982.
In 1940 he accepted an offer from William Ward Watkin to teach Architecture at Rice University and moved to Houston, where he remained until his retirement in 1979. He earned the title of Professor Emeritus and served as registrar of the University from 1965 until 1979. He also published 2 books, Handbook of Perspective Drawing (co-authored by his father) and A Walking Tour of Rice University. He served from 1954 to 1996 as Director of Building Permits and Building Inspector for Piney Point Village.
He was most active as an architect in the 1950s, when he designed houses for 2 Rice professors and for his own family – a house for which he won an Award of Merit from the Houston Chapter AIA. He was also a member of the Houston Philosophical Society and of the board of directors of the San Jacinto Girl Scouts. Morehead died on July 4, 1999 at the age of 85.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains educational materials including manuscripts and visuals for books on construction methods. Also included are "A Walking Tour of Rice University" glass plate negatives (c. 1912-1950) given to Morehead by William Ward Watkin [presumably taken by an employee of Cram, Goodhue and Ferguson and/or the photographer Schleuter] for use in Morehead's construction class. The glass slides show the construction of several buildings at Rice, including Lovett Hall, the physics building, the mechanical laboratory, power house, the chemistry building, and the football stadium. The collection also contains many photographs and slides of buildings and unique architecture at Rice.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Boxes 5-14 stored onsite in the vault at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift donated by James C. Morehead, Jr. and his son on September 23, 1985, July 9, 1997, and June 5, 1999.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Architecture; Education
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University.
- Series I: Architectural structures papers, 247086
  - Associated Schools of Architecture Learning Packages prepared in 1974 by James C. Morehead, Jr.; funded by the Kawneer/AMAZ Foundation, 247097 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Elementary Structures ES; Volume 1 of 4; Units one thru fifteen; a self-paced learning plan for students of architecture [2 copies], 247096 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Elementary Structures ES; Volume 2 of 4; Units one thru fifteen; Quizzes: Pages 1-25; Solutions: Pages 26-71 [2 copies], 247095 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elementary Structures ES; Volume 3 of 4; Units sixteen thru thirty; a self-paced learning plan for students of architecture [2 copies], 247094 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Elementary Structures ES; Volume 4 of 4; Units sixteen thru thirty; Quizzes: Pages 1-21; Solutions: Pages 22-67 [2 copies], 247093 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Associated Schools of Architecture Learning Packages prepared in 1975 by James C. Morehead, Jr.; funded by the Kawneer/AMAX Foundation, 247092 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Intermediate Structures IS; Volume 1 of 2; Seventeen unites; a self-paced learning plan for students of architecture, 247091 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Intermediate Structures IS; Volume 2 of 2; Seventeen unites; Quizzes: Pages 1-21; Solutions: Pages 22-89, 247090 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Original typescripts of Elementary Structures, Volumes 1 and 2, 247089 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Original typescripts of Elementary Structures, Volumes 3 and 4, 247088 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original typescripts of Intermediate Structures, Volumes 1 and 2, 247087 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: "A Walking Tour of Rice University" materials, 246912
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University slide presentation, 1971 (includes script and written descriptions of slides) [2 carousels], 247085 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University slide presentation, 1982: Slides 1-140 [1 carousel], 247084 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University slide presentation, 1982: Slides 141-280 [1 carousel], 247083 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University slide presentation, 1982: Slides 281-400 [1 carousel], 247082 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University by James C. Morehead, Jr. (1984), 247081 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notebook with descriptions and listings of slides, 247080 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Small box of slides labeled "Lassig", 247079 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Color separations of Rice campus buildings, areas, 247078 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University photographs (black and white, color); correspond to slides in Box 2, 247077 (Box 3)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University negatives of campus buildings, 247076 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Glass plate – site map of Princeton University, 247075 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University slides, 247074 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University negatives and contact sheets, 247073 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rice University buildings photographs, 247072 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Oswald L. Lassig research materials, 247071 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oswald L. Lassig photographs, 247070 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Research materials on Rice University buildings, 247069 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1970s and 1980s, 247068 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - William McVey Rice University sculpture research, 247067 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University or Architectural Delight on the Rice Campus – original typescript, 247066 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Rice University Studies correspondence, 247065 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Metropolitan Museum [New York[ photograph reprints, 1983, 247064 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - A Walking Tour of Rice University 1990 revision – typescript copy and notes, 247063 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn Site Map labeled July 1909, 247062 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn outline of Rice land, 247061 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn outline of Rice (labeled Cram, detailed), 247060 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn outline of Rice (labeled Goodhue, detailed), 247059 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn outline of Rice, detailed, 247058 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Hand drawn outline of Rice, detailed (different view), 247057 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: View of swamp, 247056 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: View of swamp (different view), 247055 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: General Plan of Rice, 247054 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Plot plan of Rice, 247053 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: View before construction, 247052 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: View before construction (different angle), 247051 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Terracotta vaulting over first floor – admin bldg, 247050 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Excavating for Footings, 247049 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Glass Plate Negatives: Mass Excavation, 247048 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - View of ramp for metal frames for physics bldg (Watkin pictured), 247047 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Worker doing masonry, 247046 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Roof construction, 247045 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Power house chimney, steel beams, 247044 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Power house chimney, steel beams (different view), 247043 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Centering for coal bin floor (power house), 247042 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Brick Arches and centering, 247041 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Construction slide, 247040 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - East side of engine room – power house, 247039 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - East side of engine room – power house (cracked), 247038 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Steel Beams, 247037 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Construction of physics building, 247036 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Engine Room Framework (looking down on it), 247035 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Skeleton roof and walls of physics building, 247034 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - View of construction site, 247033 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Pulley system for steel trusses, 247032 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Machinery and steel girders, 247031 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Construction slide, 247030 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Building of Arch, 247029 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Stone Arch Centering (setting Sallyport arch), 247028 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Wall forms, 247027 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Building Forms, 247026 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pier Forms pilings in basement, 247025 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Removing Forms, 247024 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Roof construction, physics building, 247023 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Placing Steel in Forms, 247022 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Placing Steel in Footings, 247021 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Placing Steel in Forms, 247020 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Forms for Tile Vault, 247019 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Tile Vault (dome over vestibule #2), 247018 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Waterproofed Wall (foundation), 247017 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Waterproofed Wall for Baker College, 247016 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Applying Waterproofing, 247015 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Roofing Tile in Place, 247014 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Diagram for Roofing Tile Construction, 247013 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Brick Arches, 247012 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Brick Arches, 247011 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Brick Detail, Mechanical lab and power house, 247010 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Brick Detail, Baker College, 247009 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Pattern Brick Work, Physics Building, 247008 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Using Brick for Test Loads (Watkin Pictured), 247007 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Brick Arches and Centering, Physics Building Cloisters, 247006 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Stone Storage Area, 247005 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Stone Arch, Old West Hall, 247004 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Sallyport Arch, 247003 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Construction stonework from a church in Bologna, Italy which is reminiscent of some of the Rice arches. (The capitals are especially reminiscent of the Chemistry building), 247002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Stone Carving, Lovett Hall, 247001 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Stone Construction, 247000 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Capitals of Column, 246999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Stone after Carving, 246998 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Setting of Stone Column, 246997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Construction on Doorway, 246996 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Close-up view of column with comic birds, 246995 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Stone column in position, 246994 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Capitals of Column (cracked), 246993 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Setting a column in place, 246992 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Close-up of column on Lovett Hall (with design), 246991 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Close-up of column on Lovett Hall (2 faces), 246990 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Close-up of column with professor carving, 246989 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Administrative building slide, 246988 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Administrative building, 246987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246986 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246985 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246983 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246982 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246981 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246980 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Administrative building (different view), 246979 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Lovett Hall (different view), 246978 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Lovett Hall (different view), 246977 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Lovett Hall (different view), 246976 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Lovett Hall (different view), 246975 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Physics building (South side from Lovett Hall), 246974 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Physics building (South side), 246973 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Physics building, 246972 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Physics building (different view), 246971 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Physics building (different view), 246970 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Mechanical engineering building slide, 246969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Cloisters slide, 246968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Cloisters slide (different view), 246967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Cloisters slide (different view), 246966 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Cloisters slide (different view), 246965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Baker, Hanszen, and Will Rice Colleges, 246964 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Will Rice College from Baker College Cloisters, 246963 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Baker College (Cracked), 246962 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Baker College Tower, 246961 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Chemistry building slide, 246960 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Chemistry building slide (different view), 246959 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Chemistry building slide (different view), 246958 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Cohen House Patio, 246957 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Cohen House Interior – hallway, 246956 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Cohen House – room with fireplace, 246955 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Cohen House Exterior, 246954 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Cohen House Exterior – patio, 246953 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Aerial View of Rice Campus (Broken), 246952 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Campus aerial view slide, 246951 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Campus aerial view slide (different view), 246950 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Campus aerial view slide (different view), 246949 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Campus aerial view slide (different view), 246948 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Aerial view of a game, new Rice Stadium, 246947 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Side view of New Rice Stadium, 246946 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - View of Stands, new Rice Stadium, 246945 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Bleachers and press box, new Rice Stadium, 246944 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Bleachers and press box, new Rice Stadium (different view), 246943 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Diagram of "Cross-section thru West Stands", 246942 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Seating Diagram for new Stadium, 246941 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Parking lot Diagram, 246940 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - General plan of Rice with new Stadium, 246939 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Proposed Bender Hall and Rice library building drawings, 246938 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Proposed Bender Hall and Rice library building drawings, 246937 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Proposed Bender Hall and Rice library building drawings, 246936 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Proposed library sketch by Cram and Ferguson Architects, 246935 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Front Elevation of a building, 246934 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Main Floor plan, Library Building, 246933 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Main floor plan, library building, 246932 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - First Mezzanine Floor plan, library building, 246931 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Second floor plan, library building, 246930 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Second mezzanine floor plan, library building, 246929 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Basement floor plan, library building, 246928 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Third mezzanine floor plan, library building, 246927 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Third floor plan, library building, 246926 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Fourth floor plan, library building, 246925 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - First floor plan, Rice Institute Memorial Library, 246924 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Second floor plan, Rice Institute Memorial Library, 246923 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Third floor plan, Rice Institute Memorial Library, 246922 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Basement floor plan, library, 246921 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Harvey S. Firestone Memorial Library at Princeton, First Floor Plan, 246920 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Bender Hall and Rice Library First Floor Plan, 246919 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Bender Hall and Rice Library Second Floor Plan, 246918 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - First floor plan for a house, 246917 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - First floor plan for another house, 246916 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - First Board of Trustees, 246915 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Commencement – procession from Mechanical Lab, 246914 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Oversize: Book layout negatives for A Walking Tour of Rice University, 246913 (Map-drawer 36)